"Do Collagen Supplements Work for Skin Aging?"
Collagen supplements have become
quite the trendy treatment
for aging skin,
available in an array of pills,
powders, and products
from bars and gummies
to collagen coffee and beer.
Social media is said to be
"inundated with paid ads
marketing
unsubstantiated claims."
What claims, if any,
can be substantiated?
The word collagen comes
from the Greek kola,
meaning "gum,"
and gen, meaning "producing."
Its gelling nature is
exemplified by Jell-O gelatin,
which is basically
just cooked collagen.
It is our most abundant protein
and the main
structural component
of most of the tissues
in our body.
For example, up to three
quarters of our skin by weight
may be pure collagen.
There are actually
dozens of different types,
but they all share
a characteristic
triple helix configuration
of coiled subunits.
What happens when we eat it?
If someone would have asked
for my educated guess
about taking collagen
before I took a deep dive
for my book How Not to Age,
I would have dismissed it
as witch-doctory woo-woo.
Eating skin for your face would
seem to make as much sense
as eating brains
to make yourself smarter
or eyeballs
to improve your vision.
After all,
when you eat proteins,
they are broken down into
their constituent amino acids,
which are then rebuilt into
any protein your body needs.
And, of all proteins to eat,
collagen is the only protein
in our food supply
that's truly incomplete.
That is, it's missing
an essential amino acid.
Other dietary proteins,
including all plant proteins,
contain all of
the essential amino acids--
in fact, that's why
they're called essential,
since animals like us
can't make them.
Collagen, though, is missing
the amino acid tryptophan.
So, the only protein source that
you couldn't live on is Jell-O,
since it effectively has
a protein quality score of zero.
But obviously that's
not all people eat;
so, significant
amounts of collagen
could be incorporated into
the diet without keeling over,
but tryptophan is special.
Randomizing people
to even a single meal
of a gelatin-based protein drink
can lead to memory impairments
within hours
due to
"acute tryptophan depletion,"
presumably due to a drop
in the brain of serotonin,
which is made from
tryptophan and doesn't just
regulate mood but learning
and memory as well.
So, the idea
of collagen supplements
never made sense to me,
but the proof is in the pudding,
or rather, perhaps,
the Jell-O.
What does the science say?
My assumption that
collagen proteins would get
completely broken down in
the digestive tract was wrong.
Feed people gelatin from
pig skin or chicken feet,
and little pieces
of collagen particles
can be found floating in
their bloodstream within hours.
Though no further tracking has
been done in humans, in rodents,
collagen fragments
from gelatin consumption
can end up in
cartilage and skin.
Now, biologically,
there is no mechanism
by which these fragments
could be directly incorporated
into new collagen,
but there may be an indirect way
collagen bits could boost
collagen deposition,
as appears to happen
in rat skin.
What about in people?
Some of the collagen studies
lack control groups.
I'm reminded of that vintage
Star Trek episode Mudd's Women,
where Kirk successfully swaps
out a youth-giving supplement
for a placebo
without the aliens noticing.
Randomized controlled trials
are scarce,
but a systematic review
and meta-analysis
of the available data
showed that,
although outcomes were mixed,
on average,
there were beneficial effects
for skin hydration,
elasticity, and roughness.
Despite some favorable results,
much of the
dermatology community
has remained skeptical,
suggesting the collagen
supplement industry may just be
flooding the zone with
poor quality, biased studies.
The studies are often funded
by collagen supplement
manufacturers,
and the overall quality of
evidence is considered to be
"limited, contradictory,"
"not particularly robust."
A 2022 review entitled
"Myths and media in oral
collagen supplementation
for the skin, nails, and hair"
in the Journal of Cosmetic
Dermatology concluded that
"Dermatologists should be aware
of the unsubstantiated
proclamations of collagen
made by companies
[which] surpass any evidence
currently supported
by the literature."
And, given
the insufficient evidence,
"collagen cannot be routinely
recommended at this time."
Moreover, the evidence
is considered to be
"particularly unconvincing"
when compared to methods more
definitely shown to have
a positive effect
on skin collagen,
such as sunscreen use,
smoking cessation,
and a healthy diet.